BU Records: Adelphian Theological Society, Inclusive: 1889-1916, undated, Bulk: 1889-1903
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Adelphian Theological Society
Inclusive: 1889-1916, undated, Bulk: 1889-1903
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/2
Adelphian Theological Society
2 document boxes and 2 oversized boxes.
The BU Records: Adelphian Theological Society consists of documents about activities associated with the Society at Baylor University. The records group contains correspondence, financial records, legal documents, and ledgers that reflect how the Society operated.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
The Adelphian Theological Society of Baylor University was created on 1889 January 5. Thirteen young ministerial students met with Dr. Rufus C. Burleson to form the organization. The four founding officers were J.S. Tanner, W.M. Hayes, S. Tammes, and J.T. Gillespie. Together, they founded the fifth society in the history of Baylor.
The principal aims of the society are to “cultivate the warmest brotherly love, sympathy, and co-operation in Christian work; to study Bible truths, and to aid every member by kindly criticism and advice.” The object of the organization was, as stated by the members, “We, the ministerial students of Baylor University, striving to prepare ourselves for the teaching of God’s Word, and realizing the advantages to be secured and the benefits to be derived from concert, unity and system of action, with a view to our spiritual, mental and social development, we do hereby resolve ourselves into an organization for the investigation of Gospel truths.” The colors of the Adelphian Society were blue and white.
The Adelphian Theological Society slowly developed a library and was largely helped by the donation of the Kimball library of 1,200 volumes of books donated by the widow of J.A. Kimball. After a few years the Adelphians grew to have one of the best collections of theological books in the Southwest. There was no mention of the Adelphians in the Baylor Round-up after 1907 as an active society.
Scope and Content
The BU Records: Adelphian Theological Society begins in 1889 and ends in 1916, although there are undated documents. Records include correspondence, literary productions, financial ledgers and documents, and legal documents. With the exception of some loose material, everything is bound in ledgers, and organized by financial, literary, and legal series. The ledgers were the responsibility of different officers within the organization. The loose materials deal with correspondence between members pertaining to financial or legal issues within the Society.
Arrangement
The BU Records: Adelphian Theological Society was organized with one folder and bound ledgers in three boxes previous to this finding aid. Currently, the collection is housed in two oversize boxes and three standard size boxes. One oversize box contains two fragile scrapbooks, which contain member certificates. The other oversize box also contains a fragile book with a very worn binding. The standard boxes contain the ledgers from the collection in addition to the loose material found in them. All of this is contained in folders. BU Records: Adelphian Theological Society is arranged in four series: I. Literary Productions, II. Legal Documents, III. Financial Documents, and IV. Correspondence.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/2. Acquired 1974-04-17
Related Resources
Related references
The Senior Class of 1896. The Baylor University Annual. Waco, Texas: 1896. Accessed on 2012 November 10.
The Senior Class of Baylor University, The Round-Up. Waco, Texas: 1907. Accessed on 2012 November 30.
The Students of Baylor University. Centennial Round-Up (1845-1945). Waco, Texas: 1945. Accessed on 2012 November 27.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.
Subjects
Theology -- Study and teaching.
Genres
By-laws.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Scrapbooks.
- Literary Productions, 1889-1907; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains ledgers and loose materials found in those ledgers, including letters from different members to the society. Also in this series is a ledger containing various stories from members of the society and other published works that they found important. Items found in folders one through five are loose materials from the scrapbooks found in oversize box five. This collection is in good to fair condition.
  - Scrapbooks: Loose Materials: Literary: Library, 1896-1899 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbooks: Loose Materials: Literary, 1898-1905 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks: Loose Materials: Committees, 1898-1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbooks: Loose Materials: Certificates, 1905-1907 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbooks: Loose Materials: Correspondence, 1905-1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Records, 1889-1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Loose Materials: Financial, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ledger: Loose Materials: Legal, 1889-1904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ledger: Loose Materials: Literary, 1904-1907 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Legal Documents, 1889-1907, undated; 2
  General condition: Good.
  This series contains a variety of loose material and bound papers concerning the operations
  of the Adelphian Theological Society. This series most notably contains the constitution of the society along with a list of the active officers. This collection is in fair to good condition.
  - Ledger: Special Library Book, 1895-1901 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Construction and By-Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1899-1905 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Adelphian Theological Society Members, 1889-1897 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ledger, 1898-1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Library Ledger, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Proceeding Records of Society, 1889-1900 (Box 4, Folder OVZ.)
  - Scrapbook: Letter and Invoice File, 1891-1898 (Box 4, Folder OVZ.)
  - Scrapbook: Gray Invoice, 1901-1907 (Box 5, Folder OVZ.)
- Financial Documents, 1889-1906; 3
  This Series includes a wide variety of financial records involving the Adelphian Society. Most of this information is located in ledgers and loose materials found in those ledgers. This collection is in fair to good condition.
  - Financial: Ledger: Loose Materials: Receipts, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ledger, 1889-1891 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Loose Materials: Correspondence, 1902-1905 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ledger: Loose Materials: Financial, 1902-1906 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer, 1892-1906 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ledger: Schedule, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1916; 4
  This series is very brief and only includes a graduation invitation dated 1916, which is in good condition.
  - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 9)